DAN KLEIN: Today we're going to talk
about methods that put the policies at
the forefront.
And rather than really talking only
about values and finding optimal
values, we're going to think hard
about the policies themselves--
this idea that there are good policies
and there are bad policies.
And then we're even going to have
methods of finding optimal policies
that work over the policies themselves
and make the policies better, rather
than simply working over the values,
trying to make the values better.
The first idea we're going to need
is the idea of policy evaluation.
And you can think of this as you've
got a policy in your hand.
Maybe it's good.
Maybe it's bad.
And what you want to know is for this
policy, which is presumably
suboptimal, how good is it?
How well will I perform
if I follow it?
For each state, what will the value
be, not under optimal action, but
under this specific policy?
So this is figuring out for a
policy what the values are.
So far we've been talking as if the
only thing we would ever want to
consider is doing the optimal action.
In the end, you usually do want
to do the optimal action.
When you consider optimal actions,
the outcome tree looks like this.
There are many actions you can take.
For each one, you figure out how good
it is and then you take the maximum.
So you consider all those actions,
and you pick the best one.
And so essentially, you
get a max node.
Expectimax did that.
It maxed over all of the actions, and
that gave you optimal values, and
therefore optimal behaviors.
So if I have a policy pi which tells
me what action to take, I no longer
have all of these choices a.
The tree looks like this.
Right now, I'm only doing what pi
tells me, not the optimal thing.
And that means the max nodes just
got a whole lot simpler.
Rather than having a whole set of
actions that they have to consider,
there's only one action permitted.
That's whatever pi says to do.
And so the tree doesn't branch
at the max node.
Of course, it still branches at the
chance node, because we don't know
what's going to happen when we
execute the action pi of s.
But from a state s, there's
only one action allowed.
It's pi of s.
That makes the tree simpler.
And it means the algorithms we're going
to have for computing values are
going to be simpler and faster, because
we don't have to worry about
maxing over the alternatives anymore.
Of course, the value at the root is
presumably going to be worse for the
tree on the right, unless pi is,
in fact, the optimal policy.
So the value you get out
depends on the policy.
But this process of computing the value
is simpler because we just prune
the tree in essence.
So one of the basic operations we had
for optimal quantities was to compute
the optimal utility of a state.
And now we're going to do that same
thing for a fixed policy.
And in a way, this is
going to be easier.
This is easier than what
we've already done.
So we imagine we've got
some policy pi.
It's presumably bad, but
we're stuck with it.
And what we're trying to do is compute
for every state s, what score I will
get, on average of course,
if I follow pi.
So the quantity we get
now is V pi of s.
The pi indicates that
we're following pi.
It used to be a star, which meant
we were acting optimally.
Now we're acting pi-like.
And this is the expected, total,
discounted rewards, cumulative until
the end of time but discounted for
starting an s and following pi.
What's this going to work out to?
Well, let's write it down.
We'd like to figure out what
V pi is for a state s.
And we need to write some equation
that's going to be a Bellman equation.
It's going to define this value in terms
of values of other states but
unrolled one level of expectimax.
That's a one-step look ahead process.
Well, the first thing we used to do is
we used to write out a maximum over
the actions.
We don't have to do that.
Because we know what action
you take from s.
You take pi of s.
What we don't know is what's going
to happen when we take it.
So we still need to consider
all the possible outcomes.
They're s prime.
When we consider all of the possible
outcomes, they each have a weight
which is still the transition
function.
The transition function takes the
state s, the action we took--
and the action we took was pi of s--
and the outcome, s prime, and it
tells us how likely s prime is.
If we land in s prime,
what will happen?
Well, we will immediately
receive a reward.
That reward depends on the state,
the action-- which is pi of s--
and the result state s prime.
And it depends on the
discounted future.
So I discount everything by gamma.
And then I plug in the value of
the landing state, s prime.
But because I'm acting according to
pi, I do not assume that I act
optimally in the future.
I assume I act pi-like in the future.
And so that's a V pi.
So again, it's the same kind of
Bellman equation, but the
max over a is gone.
OK, so now we have a recursive
relation, which is a one-step
look-ahead for the case where the policy
is fixed, and we want to figure
out what the values are.
We start at the top.
We don't max over a, because
we're stuck with pi.
But we do still average over
the outcomes s prime.
Let's take a look at an example
of policy evaluation.
You could have an agent here which
has the policy always go right.
How's this going to go.
This is going to go badly.
And you can see that agent's looking at
this map, and in its head, looking
at this map, it can run
policy evaluation.
And without actually stepping into the
fire pit, it can simulate, it could
run say value iteration or expectimax
and see that things
are going to be bad.
OK, but this is a fixed policy.
We could use this policy.
There would be outcomes.
Presumably, they'd be quite bad.
Here's another policy.
This is the policy always go forward.
In fact, this is probably
the optimal policy.
But when you have this policy in front
of you, you don't actually
know that right now.
All you know is you've got some policy
and you're supposed to evaluate it.
And so you look in your head, and
you think what will happen
if I use this policy?
And presumably the outcomes will
be better, and therefore the
values will be higher.
So here are two policies.
And I could compare them.
And for example, if one had higher
values, I could choose it, if this
were a choice I had to make.
So what are the actual values
under these policies?
We just saw a way of thinking
about the Bellman equations.
Let's see what the values
turn out to be.
Well, here they are.
These are all of the states on a grid
world, where basically the kind of
center corridor is a bridge
where you can move safely.
There's a reward at the
end at the top.
And if you fall to the left or the
right, then you receive a negative 10
when you fall onto to the firepit.
And so what you can see here is you can
see the policy always goes right.
It's not so bad, if you're on
the exit, where you have no
choice but to exit.
But anywhere else, it's pretty bad.
It's not a very good policy,
but it has values.
Super important.
States have optimal values, and they
also have values high or low for any
specific policy.
On the right, there's the policy
always go forward,
which is also optimal.
And you can see the values there.
And here the values are much better,
because they reflect
actually good actions.
They happen to be the same as the
optimal values, because this policy is
the optimal policy in this case.
OK, now how do we calculate
those values we just saw?
We basically already have the answer,
because we know if we have Bellman
equations which characterize optimal
or fixed policy values, we can
operationalize them by changing the
qualities into an assignment and then
having an iterative process that
starts at depth zero and
works its way to higher.
Depth.
So one way of computing the values
under a policy is to take these
recursive Bellman equations
and make them updates.
It's just like value iteration.
It would look like this.
You started at depth zero.
You say if I had zero time steps left,
and I was forced to follow pi, I would
receive, of course, from
any state zero.
So I create this vector of zeros,
those are V zero values,
when I follow pi.
Then I say well, if I had Vk for pi
already computed, I knew what the
score is if I follow i pi for
k time-steps averaging
over all that chance.
If I knew that, I could figure out
what it would be like to follow
it for k plus 1.
I imagine starting at some state s.
I imagine I have k plus
1 times steps left.
And I think what will happen to me?
Well, I'll take pi of s.
I don't need to max anymore.
I'll take the action pi of s.
I'll have to average over all
the outcomes, s prime.
And for each outcome, I add up the
instantaneous reward from that time
step with the discounted future rewards
from the landing state s prime
when the action resolves
until the end of time.
That's just the Bellman equation turned
into an assignment, but now
there's also these subscripts that allow
me to have a base case and work
my way up in a dynamic
programming fashion.
So that's a perfectly good idea.
This is sometimes called simplified
value iteration, because you don't max
over all of the actions.
And if you think about this, it's
actually a lot more efficient that
value iteration was.
How much time does it
take per iteration?
Well, this thing we do, we
have to do this s times--
1 for every state.
So these methods only make sense
when the number of states
is relatively small.
So you have to do this thing
for every state.
And for each state, what do you do?
You take an average over all
the possible results.
How many results could there
be from taking pi of s?
Well, there could be s of them.
It could be that every state is
connected to every state.
Usually that's not true.
Usually the actions have a smaller
number of outcomes.
But in the worst case, for every
iteration, we visit each state to do
this update, and this update has
a for loop over s primes.
And they're s many of them as well.
And so the efficiency of
this is s squared.
If you remember back to value iteration,
it was s squared a.
Because we needed to do this for every
action a from every state.
So we did it a times more.
And if you had 100 actions, it meant
it was 100 times slower.
So on the plus side valuation iteration
computed optimal values.
On the minus side, it was a factor
of a slower, which could
be very, very slow.
Of course, there are other ways to
solve this system of equations.
Because the maxes are gone, this is now
just a linear system of equations.
So actually we don't need any of this.
We can just take any system solver for
linear equations, like Matlab, and
plug them in.
Now, of course, if you think about how
you solve very large linear systems,
often the way you solve them is with
fixed point methods, which turned out
to look more or less exactly
like what we're doing here.
So there's no real magic.
But the point is once the maxes are
gone, the thing that drove us to this
particular class of solutions
actually is gone as well.
OK.
Policy evaluation was about taking a
policy and figuring out for each state
how good it was.
Now we're going to look at
the opposite direction.
What happens if I give you the values
and I ask you the question what policy
should I use if these
values are correct?
Let's think about how we would compute
the actions to take from values.
So let's imagine that somebody handed
us the optimal values V star.
So for a particular setting of grid
world, what you see here are the
optimal values.
And then we can ask questions
like how should I act?
Let's look at the interesting square
here, which is this one.
Right?
I look at that and I think, hmm, 0.89.
That's not too bad.
What should I do?
Should I choose the action north?
Should I choose the action west?
You can see for this particular setting,
this is a setting of the MDP
where you should choose to move into the
wall and do it over and over again
until you either sneak north
or south through the noise.
| kind of a weird case, but I think it
shows that you can't look at these
numbers and just tell what to do.
Because I look at these numbers, and I'd
be like oh, 0.98, that looks good.
Let's go north.
Well, it'd be great to be in
the square to the north.
The values let you figure out that
the square to the north of you
is better than you.
But they don't tell you
how to get there.
So it's actually not obvious at all,
given the values, what actions you
should take to even achieve
those values?
So how if I gave you the values and you
didn't have this helpful diagram
that also shows the policy, how would
you figure out from optimal
values how to act?
And the answer to that is basically
you've got to do expectimax.
You've got to actually unroll this thing
and figure out which was the
good action that gave rise
to these values.
Now, of course, you don't have to do
expectimax very deep, because as soon
as you start recursing into expectimax,
very soon you're going to
find that you need to plug in
some values or recurse.
And luckily, you've already
got values.
So what I'll do is I'll say I need to
consider every action a from this
state s and figure out which
is the good one.
So I need to consider every action a.
And then, for each action, I need to
consider all of the results, s prime,
that that action could have.
Now for each action a, we know the score
is going to be an average over
the s primes.
That average is going to be weighted
by the transition function.
The transition function here references
a, which is the action that
I'm considering.
And I'm going to need to try them
all, just like in expectimax.
I get a reward for the
first time-step.
And then I have my discounted future.
Now luckily the discounted future, I've
assumed I actually have already.
So this is all the expectimax
I need to do.
Now I left a space over the a, because
I'm going to compute this average,
this chance node q value,
for every action a.
Now I'm not going to actually maximize
over them, in that the
policy isn't 7.3.
It's the action that
yields the maximum.
The notation we have for that is called
arg max, which you may have
seen before.
Arg max means consider all the values,
and rather than taking the maximum,
give me the value of a, which
achieved the maximum.
OK, so here it is.
The way I get actions out of values is
I unroll one-step look-ahead for
expectimax.
And then I plug in as my evaluation
function those optimal values.
So I have to do work, because I have
to reconsider all the actions and I
need to reconsider all the
transition probabilities.
And only then can I plug in
those optimal things.
Action selection from values is
kind of a pain in the butt.
This process, by which I take values,
which may be optimal or may not, and I
compute a one-step look-ahead policy
according to them is called policy
extraction.
Because what it does is it digs out the
policy that those values imply.
However, it requires work.
It requires a one-step expectimax
from every state to reconstruct.
What about q-values.
Q-values are kind of weird.
When you think about values, you think
OK, expectimax from a state.
Great.
Then we say q-values, and
you think q-state?
What's a q-state?
A state action pair-- why am I pairing
a state and an action?
A q-state is a much less intuitive
quantity than a state.
Here's why we have a name for it.
Here's why it exists at all.
Let's imagine that we have the optimal
q-values, which means for each state
and action pair we know what we will
achieve if we choose that action.
This is what the q-values
look like in grid world.
For each state, we had four of them, at
least for the states for which we
have the four options available.
How should we act?
Let's go back to that interesting
case right here.
Here's the interesting square, where we
knew there was some way to get 0.89
and we had to reroll this expectimax
search to figure out that the way you
end up going north is actually to bang
into the wall over and over again.
Here, that's totally obvious
from the q-values.
You look north, and you say
oh, north is only 0.76.
But if I go into the
wall, that's 0.89.
The q-values make it super
easy to decide actions.
And that's why they're useful.
It is completely trivial to
do action selection when
presented with q-values.
They've essentially already unrolled
that critical layer of the max step
that you needed.
Basically you look at your state.
You take the arg max over
a of the q-values.
That's it.
Super easy.
This is an important lesson.
It's going to be especially
important next week.
It is much easier to select actions
from q-values than from values.